Guide to the Barbara Corcoran Papers 1928-2000
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Barbara Corcoran papers
1928-2000
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 856
Corcoran, Barbara, 1911-2003
8.2 linear feet
Barbara Corcoran was a popular children's writer who lived in Missoula, Montana until her death in 2003. Corcoran often chose Montana as a setting for her novels including A Horse Named Sky and My Wolf, My Friend. This collection contains correspondence, photographs, manuscripts, and biographical materials relating to Corcoran's life and work.
Biographical Note
Barbara Asenath Corcoran was born on April 12, 1911 in Hamilton, Massachusetts. She was the only child of John and Annah Corcoran. She graduated from Wellesley College in 1933 and received a Master of Arts degree in English literature from the University of Montana in Missoula in 1955. Following her graduation from Wellesley, she worked for the Federal Writer's Project and then the Navy during World War II. She also worked in advertising, for various theaters, as a playwright, in the story department at CBS television and for a celebrity news service in Hollywood, California. She also taught English at various institutions in Colorado, Kentucky, and California.
Throughout her career, Corcoran wrote articles and short stories, publishing them in newspapers and magazines. Her first children's novel, Sam was published in 1967. She left teaching to write full-time in 1969. A prolific author, she also published under the pseudonyms Gail Hamilton and Paige Dixon. Corcoran became known as a children's and young adult writer, publishing over 70 novels and earning both the William Allen White Award and the Pacific Northwest Booksellers Award. She moved back to Missoula, Montana in the early 1970s where she lived and worked until her death on November 9, 2003.
The collection contains correspondence, reviews of Corcoran's books, biographical/autobiographical materials and financial records. The major part of the collection is typed manuscripts and galley proofs of some of her many books. The collection also contains a published work she did with Bradford Angier and a book manuscript written by Bradford Angier. There are also photographs of Corcoran, her friends, and her family.
This collection has been divided into four series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1941-2000, 0.2 linear feet
Series II: Personal, 1937-1989, 1.0 linear feet
Series III: Writings, 1928-1998, 6.8 linear feet
Series IV: Photographs, circa 1940-1980, 0.2 linear feet
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
This collection was donated to Archives and Special Collections by the creator, Barbara Corcoran, in several accessions in 1974, 1976, and 1993. Following Corcoran's death, Jeanne Dixon, the executor of the estate, donated two additional accessions in 2004 and 2007.
There are no expected additions to this collection.
The University of Central Missouri holds the Barbara Corcoran Papers, another collection of her writing.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Corcoran, Barbara--Archives; Angier, Bradford
Children's literature, American--20th century
Manuscripts for publication--Montana--Missoula
Women; Literature; Missoula
Women authors, American
- Correspondence, 1941-2000; Series I; 0.2 linear feet
  This series contains correspondence received by Barbara Corcoran including fan mail, letters from friends, and communications with her publishers.
  - Correspondence, 1941, 1955 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Correspondence, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Correspondence, University of Southern Mississippi, 1997 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Correspondence, Children's Fan Mail, 1968-1972 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Personal, 1937-1989; Series II; 1.0 linear feet
  This series contains materials relating to Barbara Corcoran's personal life and finances.
  - Biographical, undated (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Biographical, Family Genealogy, undated (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Book Reviews, undated (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Book Reviews, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Clippings, 1930s (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Financial Records, Royalties, 1985, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Legal Documents, 1991, 1995 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Pamphlets, Barbara Corcoran's Books, 1971-1982 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Miscellaneous, Appointment Book, 1989 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Miscellaneous, Book Reading Record, 1988 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Miscellaneous, Playbills, 1937-1948 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 2/6)
- Writings, 1928-1998; Series III; 6.8 linear feet
  This series contains drafts, manuscripts, and galley proofs of Barbara Corcoran's many writing projects and speeches.
  - Music, Where Did The Time Go., 1975 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Poetry, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Theatrical, 1941 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Theatrical, 1955 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Journal, American Girl, 1970 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Journal, American Girl, 1970 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Journal, American Girl, 1970 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Journal, American Girl, 1971 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Journal, American Girl, 1971 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Journal, Author and Journalist, 1960 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Journal, Co-ed, 1970 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Journal, Extension, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Journal, Good Housekeeping, 1981 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Journal, Redbook, 1961 (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Journal, Woman's Day, 1966 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Journal, Woman's Day, 1967 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Journal, Glamour, 1943 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Jordan (aired on KUFM), 1998 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Jordan (aired on KUFM), 1998 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Contemporary Author's Autobiographical Series, Vol. 2, undated (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Contemporary Author's Autobiographical Series, Vol. 20, undated (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Autobiographical, undated (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Autobiography, manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Autobiography, manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Autobiography, manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Sunrise (autobiography), manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Sunrise (autobiography), manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Sunrise (autobiography), manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Sunrise (autobiography), manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Sunrise (autobiography), manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Sunrise (autobiography), manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Sunrise (autobiography), manuscript, Undated (Box-folder 4/7)
  - The Aegis articles (student publication), 1928 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - The Ghost of Spirit River, galley proof, 1968 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Sasha My Friend, galley proof, 1969 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - The Lifestyle of Robie Tuckerman, manuscript, 1971 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Don't Slam the Door When You Go, manuscript, 1972 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Don't Slam the Door When You Go, manuscript, 1972 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Don't Slam the Door When You Go, manuscript, 1972 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Don't Slam the Door When You Go, manuscript, 1972 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Don't Slam the Door When You Go, galley proof, 1972 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Don't Slam the Door When You Go, galley proof, 1972 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Don't Slam the Door When You Go, galley proof, 1972 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Lion on the Mountain, manuscript, 1972 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Lion on the Mountain, manuscript, 1972 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Lion on the Mountain, galley proof, 1972 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Lion on the Mountain, galley proof, 1972 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Silver Wolf, manuscript, 1973 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Silver Wolf, manuscript, 1973 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Silver Wolf, galley proof, 1973 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - All the Summer Voices, manuscript, 1973 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - All the Summer Voices, galley proof, 1973 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - The Young Grizzly, manuscript, 1974 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - The Young Grizzly, galley proof, 1974 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - The Young Grizzly, galley proof, 1974 (Box-folder 7/8)
  - Promises to Keep, manuscript, 1974 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Promises to Keep, galley proof, 1974 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - The Winds of Time, manuscript, 1974 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - The Winds of Time, galley proof, 1974 (Box-folder 8/4)
  - The Winds of Time, galley proof, 1974 (Box-folder 8/5)
  - A Dance to Still Music, manuscript, 1974 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - A Dance to Still Music, manuscript, 1974 (Box-folder 8/7)
  - A Dance to Still Music, galley proof, 1974 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - A Dance to Still Music, galley proof, 1974 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - A Dance to Still Music, galley proof, 1974 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Meet Me at Tamerlane's Tomb, manuscript, 1975 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Meet Me at Tamerlane's Tomb, galley proof, 1975 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - The Clown, manuscript, 1975 (Box-folder 9/6)
  - The Clown, galley proof, 1975 (Box-folder 9/7)
  - A Candle to the Devil, manuscript, 1975 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - A Candle to the Devil, galley proof, 1975 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Titania's Lodestone, manuscript, 1975 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Titania's Lodestone, galley proof, 1975 (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Titania's Lodestone, galley proof, 1975 (Box-folder 10/5)
  - May I Cross Your Golden River, manuscript, 1975 (Box-folder 10/6)
  - May I Cross Your Golden River, galley proof, 1975 (Box-folder 10/7)
  - The Search for Charlie, manuscript, 1976 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - The Search for Charlie, galley proof, 1976 (Box-folder 11/2)
  - The Search for Charlie, galley proof, 1976 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - The Search for Charlie, galley proof, 1976 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - The Search for Charlie, galley proof, 1976 (Box-folder 11/5)
  - Pimm's Cup for Everyone, manuscript, 1976 (Box-folder 11/6)
  - Pimm's Cup for Everyone, galley proof, 1976 (Box-folder 11/7)
  - Cabin in the Sky, manuscript (chapter 1-15), 1976 (Box-folder 11/8)
  - Cabin in the Sky, manuscript (chapter 16-30), 1976 (Box-folder 12/1)
  - Cabin in the Sky, galley proof, 1976 (Box-folder 12/2)
  - Cabin in the Sky, galley proof, 1976 (Box-folder 12/3)
  - Axe-time, Sword-time, manuscript, 1976 (Box-folder 12/4)
  - Axe-time, Sword-time, galley proof, 1976 (Box-folder 12/5)
  - Axe-time, Sword-time, galley proof, 1976 (Box-folder 13/1)
  - Summer of the White Goat, manuscript, 1977 (Box-folder 13/2)
  - Abigail, manuscript, 1981 (Box-folder 13/3)
  - Wolf at the Door, manuscript, 1993 (Box-folder 13/4)
  - Wolf at the Door, manuscript, 1993 (Box-folder 13/5)
  - Wolf at the Door, manuscript, 1993 (Box-folder 13/6)
  - Wolf at the Door, correspondence re:, 1993 (Box-folder 13/7)
  - Ebony, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 14/1)
  - Ebony, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 14/2)
  - Ebony, manuscript, rough draft, undated (Box-folder 14/3)
  - Ebony, manuscript, not used, undated (Box-folder 14/4)
  - Ebony, manuscript, (rough material), undated (Box-folder 14/5)
  - The House on Blank Street, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 14/6)
  - The View from Here, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 14/7)
  - Paradise First Class, A Maggie Dexter Adventure, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 15/1)
  - The Long Journey, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 15/2)
  - Midnight and High Water, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 15/3)
  - Lazy Boy, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 15/4)
  - Where is Black Thunder?, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 15/5)
  - Sun on the Half Moon, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 16/1)
  - The Cherub and My Sainted Grandmother, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 16/2)
  - The View from Here, manuscript, undated (Box-folder 16/3)
  - Untitled, manuscript (pages 3-194), undated (Box-folder 16/4)
  - Edge of Fear, manuscript (by Bradford Angier), undated (Box-folder 16/5)
  - Ask for Love and They Give You Rice Pudding (book by Bradford Angier and Barbara Corcoran), 1977 (Box-folder 16/6)
- Photographs, circa 1940-1990; Series IV; 0.2 linear feet
  This series contains photographs of Barbara Corcoran as well as her friends and family.
  - Photographs, Barbara Corcoran and Family, undated (Box-folder 17/1)
  - Photographs, Barbara Corcoran's early years, undated (Box-folder 17/2)
  - Photographs, Acquaintances, undated (Box-folder 17/3)